[Music]
welcome to future focus a video series
brought to you by ICICI Lombard today we
have with us gopal bhatta children the
CFO and CEO of ICICI Lombard as you all
know ICICI Lombard is a leading non-life
insurance company today we are here to
talk about risk management in these
unprecedented times Gopal is going to
share with us insights from ICICI
Lombard and also insights for you as an
audience
welcome to the show sir how are you I'm
good Michele thank you so much and good
morning everyone
it's always great feeling to be here and
happy to kind of share elements of risk
management that we fundamentally have
implemented our business is
fundamentally risk management I think
let me put it in that context and and as
we shall rightly describe will be
extremely happy to kind of share our
thoughts we are also gaining experiences
as we speak but extremely happy and
delighted to kind of speak on the areas
which we think will be relevant and
useful to all of you so before we get on
to the subject you joined ICICI Lombard
in 2002 when it was a very young company
you just finished your CA and your
company secretary and you'd come in at a
time when a crisis are just ended like
the.com crisis and here we are in the
midst of another crisis and risk
management is back to the center of
everything you know how did you how do
you manage to understand these changing
trends you know I wanted to talk to you
about a couple of things based on your
experience before we go on to the main
question no absolutely I think that's a
good question to start off with Vishal I
think if you have which is what I said I
think if you look at it from a nice ASIS
numbered standpoint fundamentally we
take the risk of companies and we kind
of get the companies away from their
risks that they are exposed to and we
kind of in in dignified in case if any
losses are being experienced by them as
a result of some of these crisis events
we may
good those losses I mean that's all the
journey starts for us so in that sense
as an organization as a company we are
into risk management all the times and
as it is rightly said the thing starts
from within I mean you have to kind of
while you are advocating a lot of risk
management practices for companies but
more importantly you need to see as to
how you have instituted a risk
management capability within the
organization which will fundamentally
stand the test for meeting any risks
that the company would be exposed in the
first place and our journey to risk
management in fact to be honnest started
almost like about 15 years back we
didn't start off with an enterprise disc
management frameworks in the time when
we started operations because we also
wanted to gain ground in terms of our
experiences and we kind of thought about
it somewhere around 2006 2007 to kind of
start looking at putting in some kind of
a framework within which we will be able
to work as an organization and we have
been kind of learning ground over the
years and Hana Street was in 2009 2010
is when we really thought about putting
a formal erm framework which will kind
of fit the organization at large that's
how the old journey started and from
there all and as I said every experience
is a learning experiences more
importantly when you come across
crisises they kind of teach a lot
because it's a testimony of what kind of
practices you have put into and even
this crisis as we speak obviously of an
unprecedented scale again it teaches a
lot in terms of how companies have to
function when you look at it from an
earing perspective great points are you
also wrote a current blog a recent blog
which talked about risk management you
know in that you outline a few important
points are the roles and
responsibilities can you share some
roles and responsibilities of yourself
that you are handling the situation in
such an unprecedented time piece
absolutely
Vishal again that's a great question to
ask so again as I said I think being a
responsible company I think we are
driven by our core fundamentals of
corporate governance
and risk management and as I said in
these times we continue to remain
committed fully so far as meeting the
service requirements of our customers
are concerned now when you look at it
from the standpoint of a responsibility
or a challenge in these times one of the
core things that stands the test is what
is it that you stand for as an
organization I mean that's the pillar in
which the foundation of the organization
is laid out and if you look at one of
the things that Isis Lombard has
advocated at all times is profitable
growth I think that's the theme that we
have kind of driven the organization
with and that along with ensuring
protection to our balance sheet at all
times has been at the core of the four
friend within which we drive all our
responsibilities and the challenges that
we have in so far is meeting the
requirements of the customers are
concerned the couple of responsibility
that comes immediate when you look at
this scenario one is around the I mean I
will try to talk about three aspects the
first and the foremost aspect is
employee safety because that's the first
responsibility that comes when you look
at any organization that is in the
service industry employees comes first
and so therefore you have to ensure the
safety and the well-being of the people
so that's one of the four core
fundamentals that I would kind of lay
emphasis on when it comes to
responsibility in such situations the
second is business continuity because
end of the day as we say employees can
come employees may leave but the
organization has to kind of survive for
the next X number of years so hence to
that extent while events of a pandemic
nature or otherwise may happen
institutions have to kind of completely
reorient their business models and look
at ways of sustaining operations insofar
as instituting appropriate business
continuity practices so that's a second
area where I would kind of lay an
important responsibility on and the
third aspect which is more with respect
to our own internal disc assessment
because when I said as an organization
you have built an erm framework in place
you need to make sure that you do a
comprehensive risk assessment of your
internal process
and see where do you stand in these
uncertain times now let me quickly touch
upon some of the initiatives or let's
say aspects that we have taken in to ask
into factor when we look at it from an
employee safety standpoint the first and
the foremost I mean pretty much so I'm
sure you have heard a lot we also kind
of did in all our office promises
temperature checking for our people and
if at all any of our employees showed
any symptoms of this particular virus
being contracted because you need to
kind of make sure that those set of
people for whatever reasons need to be
treated differently so that the rest of
the organization is able to function as
business as usual the second thing that
we did was obviously in these times a
lot of us I mean particularly we are in
the business of service we tend to do a
lot of physical trainings and
conferences for most of our employees as
well as for our service providers so in
these times we again said let's keep
that on hold and we can always as we are
doing this digitally I think the thought
process is try and see if you can kind
of do a lot of those in the digital
format the third aspect I think what we
did was completely put in that sense
full stop to all kind of travels whether
it is domestic or international because
again we didn't want the employees
well-being to be compromised and the
final piece it's always important not
just to have a committee at the top I
mean while you can have a tone from the
top in managing things but the eyes and
the ears of the organization is always
have to be on the ground so we kind of
adopted a two-layered approach when it
comes to when it came to sports so while
at the at the management end we had the
man calm but at the operating level we
had those point of contacts who also
acted as the eyes and ears for the
organization so those were some of the
measures that we took insofar as
employee safety is concerned quickly on
the internal risk assessment which was
the second pillar that I kind of spoke
about as an organization we have and erm
framework in place
the ERM framework broadly kind of works
around five key risk categories one is
credit risk market underwriting
operational and strategic now each of
this risk areas kind of has an impact or
has a responsibility in the way of how
you manage it
let me get quickly take you through each
of them if you take credit risk we are
exposed to credit risks on working with
our reinsurance partners just like we
take a risk from customers we also do a
risk transfer to reinsurance partners we
have to ensure that we do a
comprehensive risk assessment of those
reinsurance partners so that any
possibility of recoverability from those
three insurers are being looked at very
closely so that's a create risk
monitoring that we do on the market risk
side I mean if you look at an insurance
company's operations we do write or
let's say we underwrite risk of
customers but we also manage the funds
of people because we invest that in
various securities and in the process we
are exposed to market risk so again
there becomes a responsibility for us to
very closely monitor the assets in which
you have kind of invested so that you
don't run any kind of risk in terms of
recoverability of those investments and
at the same time there is equally a
responsibility to ensure that you have
adequate liquidity because only when you
have liquidity in the portfolio is when
you are able to manage most of the
things
so hence market risks milk marketers
becomes equally an important priority on
the underwriting risk that forms the
core of our business and in these times
there is a responsibility for us to
still continue exhibiting underwriting
service the question is how do you get
that done so there again I think
thankfully the level of investments that
we have done on the digital capability
we have been able to do a lot of virtual
risk inspections even in these times we
have been able to carry out a lot of
let's say virtual claim service and in
the process you are able to as I said
run the business as a business as usual
scenario
so again underwriting risk assessment
becomes of paramount importance
critic operational risk is equally
important in this times because couple
of reasons one you know system risk
becomes off at heightened levels because
all of us are now getting used to let's
say a work from home environment and
this by itself poses a lot of challenges
and you need to make sure that your
system related information security
aspects are completely assist and all
kind of endpoint security is what you
are required to Institute they are all
up and running so that employees are
able to still function as effectively as
they could and in the process still
there is no compromise of customer data
or for the matter of fact even there is
no leakage of data that the organization
gets exposed to so ends operational risk
is of paramount importance so there
comes a responsibility to manage that
aspect and finally on the strategic risk
side a reputation risk is of great
significance because an operation
fundamentally stands for the brand that
it is associated with and unless and
until you don't manage the brand
effectively you can significantly be put
to test so there again I think we tend
to look at I mean these days there are
lot of avenues available by which you
can do those social media tracking we
also pretty much end up doing a lot of
those so that at the end of the day we
just want to make sure that from a
reputation standpoint we don't lose our
brand's credibility so those are all
aspects that I would say insofar as the
responsibilities in these times are
concerned and you asked one more
important element Vishal which was on
insofar as challenges are concerned now
if you look at challenges let me look at
the various stakeholders that we render
service to its customers first right so
in these times on the one side while
there is a challenge in the way you
operate but equally there is a need for
you to exhibit service to the customers
so that's by itself is an inherent
challenge and you need to kind of
capacities the institution by which you
are able to meet the requirement of the
customers so that's one of the
challenges that you are kind of exposed
with as an insurance company we tend to
work with distributors because when you
call of distributors its agents it's my
bank partners it's let's say my dealer
partners so there are various
distributors that you kind of work with
and again in these times it's important
for us to handle them to make sure that
they are able to adopt digital
technology because as I said you need to
continue business to the extent it can
be as usual and to and to that diction
there is a challenge for us to ensure
that there is acceptance of the wave we
have created the organization we also
want the intermediation to be
capacitated as well so you need have a
challenge to meeting the requirement of
the distributor there is a regulatory
angle because in these times the
regulator comes out with a lot of let's
say regulatory guidelines keeping in
mind the policyholder interest so and
there is a lot of compliance
requirements that they have eased but at
the same time you have to make sure that
as an organization you stand to the
requirement of the regulatory norms that
are being laid down so again there's a
challenge to meet the various regulatory
guidelines that will get laid out and
the final piece is there is equally a
challenge that you have with respect to
our shareholders as well because equally
shareholders while they understand the
situation but at the same time they
would logically expect reasonable growth
in profits insofar as the organization
is concerned so that in a nutshell is
what I would say are the various nuances
of responsibilities and the challenges
that we are exposed to as a company
very good answer said I mean in a sense
I want to straight away move into
balance sheet protection because all
those responsibilities that you
mentioned protect your balance sheet and
focus on you know how to fight the
volatility right there is increased
volatility going forward so would you
recommend that protecting the balance
sheet is a single most important factor
at this point of time and focus on
growth at all cost
and where you see growth coming from I
think in these times even customers tend
to value a lot of companies which are on
a very strong solid footing and that
would be evident by the balance sheet
strengths that you have at the same time
would value you for the extent of
capital adequacy or solvency that you
are able to exhibit relative to the
minimum norms that are prescribed by the
regulator and at the same time they
would equally look for the level of
corporate governance that you are able
to exhibit as an organization and since
you specifically touched upon the aspect
of balance sheet protection as I said
one of the core risks that we write as a
company is my writing risk and in when
I'm underwriting risk particularly let's
say for large factories there is a need
for us to undertake physical risk
inspection because only when you are
able to understand the risk of
effectively is how you are able to price
for the assets that you are insuring now
in these times it's very difficult for
us to carry out any form of a physical
risk inspection but at the same time the
fact that you are ensuring the risk
requires you to come out with a solution
which still meets the requirement of
underwriting and at the same time you
don't put your balance sheet to risk so
what we have done again over the years
the journey that we have traversed in
respect of our investments in technology
we have been able to undertake virtual
risk inspections and these mechanisms
have been created by which we are able
to carry out this virtual inspections
prior to underwriting the risks and in
the process there is a live video
streaming that happens of this
inspection survey that we do and thereby
we are able to kind of underwrite the
risk at the same time and ensuring that
our balance sheet is not exposed to
undue risks that could come and hit us
in the future so that's one example of
how we are kind of managing the balance
sheet risk when it comes to the core
aspect of underwriting even on the
claims side I mean one of the key
requirements while the extent of claims
could be slightly lower in these times
but equally for the claims that come
through it's important for us to ensure
that claim service continues now there
again I think some of the investments
that we have done is on the motor side
we can do a live video streaming of the
motor assessment of claims on the
property side I mean there
very recent examples where there was a
factory which got impacted on account of
damages in these times so we were able
to deploy drones and survey the location
and in the process we are able to kind
of assess the extent of damage with
otherwise we would not have been able to
do unless and until we would have
invested in those capabilities so again
we are ensuring that the customer aspect
is taken care of and equally the risk
that is associated to the company is
appropriately managed through technology
based interventions so there again it's
a case of how we are able to protect our
balance sheet and so far as your other
thing which you asked on growth I think
in these times we have actually seen
couple of growth opportunities getting
played out now let me give an example of
two three areas how we see growth
playing out for us on the corporate side
one of the things that Isis Illume bird
has done over the years is built direct
relationship with corporates and that
stands as a testimony in these times
when the corporates generally as I said
would want to place an insurance with
the company which is time and tested and
they just want to kind of make sure at
this times not to look about for an
alternate insurance partner so and April
1 as we all know is a big day for
corporate renewals because most of the
corporates mirror their renewals to the
financial year cycle and thank happy to
report that most of the corporates that
were due for renewals on April 1 we have
been able to kind of get those renewals
and that has seen reasonable level of
growth momentum sustaining the small and
the mid corporates within that has been
an area of focus for the last 3-4 years
in particular for us and there I think
we have significantly advocated use of
digital capability through robotic
assistance driven mechanism we call it
as Myra my robotic assistance and in
these times and particularly for the
month of April and May we run a campaign
on the SME side and happy to report that
almost 90% of the policies that we have
sold on the SME side has been able to be
through digital adoption and the growth
momentum is quite positive
so SME is looking very good for us
quickly talking about the retail side if
you look at on motor we all know that
there is no growth happening or new
vehicle sales I mean because most of the
Williams and dealerships are pretty much
not functioning completely while in the
last week or so we have seen some kind
of relaxation happening but at least
till now most of them were closed so the
only Avenue through which most of these
points of distribution are able to make
margins let's say the dealer's is to be
able to continue retaining the existing
customers of theirs and a lot of
emphasis of us has been to kind of
promote retentions or print continued
renewals of the existing customers and
there we did make an acquisition in
quarter three of the last financial year
which called from unboxed technologies
and today in these times that particular
acquisition has come in very handy
because we have been able to deploy the
crm platform at the points of
distribution and we have been able to
significantly make the benefit of being
able to retain a larger number of
customers so again we see growth
momentum sustaining on the motor side as
well and finally on the health side this
is an event like any other catastrophic
event it is an event of a pandemic
nature which impacts the health of all
of us and as I'm sure if you would have
asked this question three years back let
me ask to you Vishal who do you have
taken a health insurance cover maybe
three or five years back no I actually
not I would have not taken a
comprehensive comprehensive covered or
even for the matter of fact he would
have polled the people of thousand
people three years back and asked them
to raise hands and how many of them
would have had a health insurance
covered why I would not be surprised if
very few number of hands would have kind
of gone up now that's a state of
situation where we are in so far as
health penetration is concerned and
events of a pandemic nature clearly
impacts the health of all of us and it
that by itself presents an opportunity
and today the point that you made
while you would have taken some form of
health insurance covered but the extent
of coverage would not be adequate you
look at yourself what kind of course we
incur while going to an Hospital while
you may not want to have that situation
coming through but indeed if it does
happen the extent of money that we have
to shell out is significant
so again health clearly presents an area
of opportunity for growth and there is a
clear silver lining that exists insofar
as that particular segment is concerned
so in a nutshell that is what I would
say in terms of how we are protecting
our balance sheet and at the same time
looking at different segments in terms
of growth leavers as well okay it's a
great point again I have two questions
combined now I think it's easy because
we've covered a lot of it there are
emerging risks because of the co 819
situation and there is an existing risk
yes okay and you've often said that risk
management should be you know not a
compliance function but a business
function yes right how do you assess the
situation at this point in time
organizations have to handle emerging
risks you know current risks and make
sure that it's not a compliance function
who do you go and tell in the
organization that please look at it as a
partner function and let's manage this
risk together so I think let's look at
it this way right I think as I said it's
all about let's say the culture of the
organization I think the it's if you
have a culture which kind of ensures
that every employee of the organization
is sensitive about the function that he
or she is handling then they by itself
understand what risks that they are
exposed to so to that extent I would say
the foremost point which I would make is
with respect to what kind of a culture
does the organization imbibe and if you
have a will lay it down culture across
the organization then to that extent
managing risks in even in these
adversities or even in these uncertain
times seems to be relatively much more
easier now let me look at couple of
risks that could be risks in the past
and certain risks which
we could kind of face as we get through
this event let me talk the ones which is
the latter part I mean some of the new
new-age risks that we are exposed to in
these times which becomes of much more
significance now the point that I made
was as I said I am sure every
organization is looking at one in these
times to have most of the people working
from home which is but natural to have
that situation in place and that by
itself opens up a set of risks that we
are exposed to on the cybersecurity
friend and we know the importance of
cybersecurity there have been instances
of wanna cry petia and similar kind of I
mean we can keep taking names and these
are events which have in that sense put
organizations to test and therefore in
these critical times while there is a
need from a business standpoint to have
your people operating from your homes
but equally at the backend there is a
need for you to have your information
security team up and running and again
in a sector in which VR regulator
mandates us two things one they ensures
that you have an appropriate information
security policy to be put in place which
acts as a governance governing mechanism
which is approved by the board but more
importantly there is a designated chief
information security officer who has to
be an employee of the company and who
will be responsible for instituting
various security control measures so
that the organization is in that sense
protected from various vulnerabilities
that we are exposed to so to that extent
you also have a chief information
security officer and thirdly from a
governance standpoint what we have also
done between the board and the CISO we
have created an information security
committee which comprises of members of
the management committee who tends to
have an oversight on the various aspects
of information security so the first
aspect is culture the second aspect is
governance so that you have an
appropriate governance structure through
which you are able to manage this now
coming to specifics in terms of what you
can
in order to address the cybersecurity
related risks in this environment I
think what we have done is one we have
taken a lot of initiatives in kind of
sending a lot of mailers so far as the
companies are concerned because these
days you tend to get a lot of links you
get a lot of emails saying that if you
click this you will get whatever the
benefits are so in that sense we have
done a lot of educational mailers
educational videos that have been kind
of put in place so that you are able to
manage the security risk that you are
exposed to that's one the second thing
when you are equipping your employees to
work from home there is a need for you
to protect the customer data as well as
prevent any form of unauthorized use of
the data that resides with the people
and what we have instituted again is
insofar as various endpoint Security's
are concerned now endpoint Security's
could be use of various USBs and similar
kind of access drives is something that
we have prevented for the organization
at large so while you can continue
working in the hardware assets which are
already kind of screened and
appropriately monitored but at least
insofar as any kind of data leakage or
data theft is concerned I think there is
a lot of endpoint security that has been
instituted insofar as data protection is
concerned the second aspect which we
have done also to ensure that we have
the information security protected is a
lot of fishing activities is what we
carry out I mean we kind of send mailers
saying that you will get five days off
if you click this link that's a classic
way to test out if people get fished or
not now in the process a lot of us may
click and if you further click on the
further links then automatically there
is a pop-up that comes and says that you
have been fished so and that by itself
is an awareness that gets created in the
minds of people and
and again there are grids in terms of
actions that are being taken in case if
one persists continuously on various
fish fishing attacks that we carry out
so in the process again you are able to
kind of manage the risk associated with
cyber security and I also understand we
spoke so much about risk risk appetite
and risk tolerance know who should set
the standards is is there a case for
setting standards to measure an
organization's appetite in tolerance
when you look at well established
standards whether it is the ISO standard
or whether it is let's say the CUSO
standards that describe requirements on
companies all of them lay emphasis on
one of the most important aspects which
is thrown from the top because that sets
the context or the tone for the risk
appetite that is being set for the
organization so that's very very
important and from our standpoint again
the risk appetite is something that gets
set at the board level because the board
determines basis the businesses that we
are into we kind of set what kind of
appetite that we want to set for
ourselves as an organization and then
comes in terms of governance we do have
the Risk Committee of the board which
oversees our adherence to the risk
update that has been said and then you
have let's say the management who kind
of takes it forward insofar as
compliance to the risk appetite
statement that is laid out but the most
important thing is setting a tone in so
from the top and there again if you look
at from a nice little home but
perspectives one of the things again we
are possibly the first Indian company at
that point of time way back in April
2008 a team when there was this ISO
31000 2018 standard that came into place
it certifies institutions all risk
management practices and what they look
for is three aspects one is the risk of
earnings that domination has said second
is a risk culture that again the
institution has adopted in their erm
practices and the third is the internal
processes that the organization has
instituted in so far as the control and
self assessment framework is that said
so
when we got this ISO 31000 standard
compliance done through british standard
institution we were the first Indian
company at that point of time to be
certified under the ISO 31000 2018
standard now that by itself in that
sense give us some credence insofar as
governance culture and our processes are
concerned and when it comes to appetite
of my thought processes you should set
your appetite only with two or three key
matrices you cannot have an appetite
statement which runs into let's say a
full page in terms of number of
appetizers that you want to set for
yourself is an obligation but more
importantly when you set those two or
three appetite as a part of risk
appetite statement it's important to
kind of merge it with the of national
objective that you have I mean as a
company you can have a visual on what is
it that you want to be known for your
appetite should revolve around it so
that's the foremost requirement in
second aspect when you look at an
appetite it is it can be either a
quantitative statement or it can be
qualitative statement there's nothing
wrong in either which face when you look
at defining an appetite for the
organization but my personal preference
is to have a qualitative assessment or a
qualitative risk appetite laid down or
quantitative risk appetite laid down so
that the ease of measurement against the
appetite becomes relatively better when
it comes to tolerances unlike where I
said it will be tone from the top
insofar as tolerances are concerned
because these are aspects that impacts
individual risk elements of the
organization it has to be bottoms up
because these are people who are
actually running the operations running
the shop and in the process they are
kind of actually experiencing the risk
that they are exposed to the does
technology play a major role here in
tracking appetite and tolerance
absolutely I think when you look at the
appetite is more like I would say
high-level appetite statement that gets
defined but definitely when it comes to
tolerances there is a need for
you have a technology which can aid you
to kind of one look at what has been the
actual outcomes visibly the tolerances
that have been said and in the process
give you a mechanism by which you are
able to know the various triggers that
can get alerted and again swing into
action now a classic example some of the
risks that I kind of outlined is let's
say let me take a simple example of a
market risk a market is today is the
most important risk element when you
look at it from the current event
standpoint and you need to have a
triggered which tells you like because
of the market fall of whatever
percentage what has been the impact on
your portfolio that impact to their
portfolio impacts your solvency or
impact your capital adequacy how do you
have enough capital to be able to meet
the fall in top prices one such examples
of how you can kind of monitor your
tolerances similarly when it comes to
operational risk I think one of the
risks that maybe I did did not speak at
length is fraud I mean in these
uncertain times there is a lot of
tendency for people to do frauds I mean
if you go back to 2008 times or whenever
you see have seen any crisis is playing
out because people are stretched
companies are stretched for their
profits individuals are stretched
because of their income levels are
relatively lower there is a tendency on
people to commit some form of a fraud or
the other so hence you need to make sure
that your fault
fraud tolerances should kind of trigger
immediate alerts so that you can
immediately swing into action and you
are able to course-correct
the need of the earth the economy
firstly do you see a silver lining okay
and how many bounced back you know there
have been questions from the audience
saying limping back or normalcy or
bouncing back right I would rather have
bouncing back because you're all working
and we all want to have good lines what
are your thoughts in the con let's talk
about the macros at this point of time
all this country come back along with it
all those companies and offer those
great jobs from a macro standpoint if
you
non life insurance this was a sector
that was opened up to private
participation in 2001 if you look at
over the last 20 years the sector has
grown at a compounded rate of 17% which
is almost two and half times the growth
in GDP of the country and you've given
growing at 17% levels hardly you will
see industry is growing at 17% Carragher
over a 20-year period but despite that
if you look at one of the measures of
monitoring is insurance penetration as a
percentage of GDP if you look at the
indian market it's at point nine seven
percent if you look at global average
its 2.8 percent if you look at the BRIC
countries they all raise I mean
particularly when you look at Brazil
when you look at China when you look at
South Africa they are all having
penetrations which occur in excess of
between 1.5 percent to 2 percent levels
India stands at 0.97% so that by itself
is a huge potential insofar as the macro
numbers are concerned now when you come
to specifics let's talk three key
product lines where one sees a silver
lining
let's take motor if you see motor is by
far the largest product line for the
market 40 percent of the industry less
is motor insurance all the 24 crores
vehicles that are plying on the road
more than 50 percent of the vehicles do
not have an insurance that's the reality
of the situation right the while they're
having some regulatory changes that have
happened in the last 1 and 1/2 years but
more than 50 percent of the vehicles
today are these without an insurance now
currently again as I said we can speak
about new vehicle sales not being there
we have to focus on renewals but the
long-term prospect of the ability to
convert some of this non penetrator or
under penetrated segments into the ambit
of insurance is a huge opportunity let
me ask you we shall any guesses on what
proportion of what proportion of the
population has got a health insurance
covered say 2 percent so let's say 2
percent so that could be more on the
individual side now when you look at
health insurance it's a cover that an
individual takes for self or family it
lawyer takes as a coverage for their
employees or it could be a government
that can sponsor a MassHealth program
for the vulnerable section of the
society today if you look at what you
said is absolutely right in an
individual context that penetration is
actually 3% but but when you see your
bang go on you're almost there but when
you look at the larger picture in terms
of all of these three segments put
together that number roughly stands at
about one third only one-third of the
country is in some form of an insurance
or the other so there is a huge Headroom
available in terms of the opportunity on
the health insurance pace and by the way
when you talk about health insurance
today you are only talking of
hospitalization insurance our
out-of-pocket spends which is what we
end up spending for visiting a doctor
visiting a Diagnostic Center ordering
medicines through a pharmacy chain
availing of an ambulance service asking
for a second opinion
now all of these services is today not
covered through insurance at all and it
roughly constitute two thirds of our
health care spends and that's not
covered through insurance today at all
that's an opportunity and that's where
again I see somebody significantly
looking at tapping into the OPD segment
so that's an opportunity there take the
corporate space particularly SME and
when I say these are small corporates
which also have to ensure their assets
and ensure their people very few number
of corporates insure their people and a
limited extent of coverage is more even
they take insurance for their assets as
well so on the SME side again there is a
significant prospect insofar as growth
is concerned so in these times of in
that sense a possible gloom and doom for
the in the short term I think from our
standpoint from a nice is a numbered
standpoint we are very very optimistic
while there can be some temporary pain
as we speak let's say for fi 2021 but
insofar as the long-term potential of
the segment and the sector is concerned
it's quite enormous and there is also a
study that has been done by some of the
global reinsurers says if the country is
at a per capita level
1,500 to 2,000 dollars which is where we
are at this point of time the growth of
the insurance sector will continue to be
two to two and half times the GDP of the
country so you would be saying that it
is going to be bouncing back and not
limping man my take on this will be as I
said fill the time we are subject to
this levels of lockdown there will
always be an apprehension on people to
get back to roads get back to buying an
asset so you will see some kind of a
temporary challenges insofar as growth
is concerned but there what is more
important is again the organizational
capability to be having a multi-product
multi-channel most multi customer that
will help them to at least kind over
this difficult times and so once things
comes back to reasonable normalcy there
is no reason why you should not see
growth momentum kind of coming back now
the question is whether it will come
back in h2 of the current here whether
it takes maybe more than a year to come
come back I think we will have to wait
for the jury to be played out but at
least from our standpoint we are
extremely excited and positive insofar
as the growth momentum returning back to
normalcy okay great answer on a personal
note how are you spending time spending
time with family how are you spending
time for yourself what are you doing
that's always a difficult one right in
these times when you are ready where at
home whenever exposed to this kind of a
situation you always want to kind of go
out maybe reach out to people talk to
them is something that you would always
want that happening but I think what
they try to do is I think largely on
family person and therefore to that
extent I like to spend time of course
with my all members of the family but
more importantly my son he's 11 years so
he is trying to learn a lot of things
trying to explore experiment with lot of
stuff being at home I have hardly been
able to get so much time to spend time
with otherwise normally I would say I'm
only in the night and maybe early in the
morning that's those so in that extend
yes I spend a lot of time with my family
and the second thing is I think I try to
also do my daily routine exercise
I spend at least about 30 minutes
because it is extremely important to
keep your body and mind flexible again
in these times so you have to be so that
you mind tend to work sharply so do
those routine exercises every day and
thirdly try to do a little bit on the
sporting side as well while at this
times one is not able to do that but
they generally like playing badminton
and more importantly I like also this
music so that's how I kind of stay
engaged Gopal you've been a wonderful
guest and I'd love to host you again
thanks for being on future purpose thank
you I see I say hello Boyd
thank you for everyone including you is
in these times please do stay safe stay
healthy that's very very important for
all of us to come out of the situation
thank you thank you everybody we look
forward to having you on another episode
of future focus very soon bye Gopal the
next thanks we shall
[Music]